SUMMARY

Data Scientist/Analyst or related mid-level opportunity to apply machine learning and statistical skills to analyze big dataset including future predictions; Over 4 years of experience on data analysis with Excel and VBA; Over 4 years of pore pressure prediction analysis from real-time and offset data; Familiar with writing SQL query writing and connecting databases to/from Java platform; Practical knowledge on data Scientist Toolbox, getting and cleaning data, exploratory data analysis, regression models, reproducible research, statistical reference and machine learning algorithms; Familiar with statistical analysis and predictive modeling with basic knowledge of SQL; Competent ability to develop hypothesis and test them; Practical knowledge Python and R libraries: Familiar in BI visualization tools; Two years of experience on geospatial analysis, ArcGIS and multispectral image algorithms; Excellent verbal and written communication skills with advanced computer skills; More than 6 years experience in the oil/gas exploration and drilling industry

CONTACT

■ benhurtedros02@gmail.com

**** 713-859-8352

♀ Houston, TX

in https://www.linkedin.com/in/benhurtedros-18821428/

• https://github.com/Bengigna/Data-Science-Career-Track

EDUCATION

Springboard

Certificate Data Science 2017

John Hopkins University through Coursera

Certificate Data Science Specialization 2016

Bowling Green State University

Msc Geology 2011 Graduate Certificate Geospatial Technology 2011

University of Asmara

Bsc Geology 2002

EMPLOYMENT

Berger Geoscience, LLC

Pore Pressure Data Analyst

Houston, TX Jun 2013 to Apr 2017

• Analyzed pore pressure related data of deep water oil/gas wells of Gulf of Mexico in real-time

- Predicted pore pressure in real-time from offset wells best fitted models
- Accomplished exploratory data analysis work on pore pressure-fracture gradient data (PPFG)
- · Analyzed PWD data to detect any anomaly in downhole pressure using Excel Macros

Horizon Well Logging, LLC

Tulsa, OK Feb 2011 to May 2013

Wellsite and Geosteering Data Analyst

- Analyzed survey and log data to land horizontal wells into target zone
- · Reviewed and evaluating all aspects of wireline open-hole logging data on site
- · Correlated real-time mudlogs and gamma/resisitivity logs with offset well data
- $\bullet \quad \hbox{Communicated daily geological drilling information/geosteering updates with an operation geologist}$

Bowling Green State University

Bowling Green, OH Jan 2009 to Feb 2011

Research and Teaching Assistant

- Applied LandSat based reflectance algorithms to map contaminant sludge concentration
 Created Modis data based algorithms to map the concentration of toxic cyanobacteria in Great Lakes
- · Predicted possible gold sites using algorithms based on ASTER spectral reflectance band ratio data
- · Analyzed remote sensing and geographic information systems (GIS) related data for class projects

PROJECTS

Predicting Monthly Electricity Sale Revenue of Residential Sector in the United States

Nov 2017 to

- · Wrangled and cleaned the data, and performed exploratory data analysis
- Set up test harness and utilize ARIMA models for prediction
- Conduct model testing and evaluation

Finding Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Facilities with Patients' Data using Unique Patterns in Dialysis Patt

- Carried out data wrangling and cleaning, and applied feature selection engineering
- · Did exploratory data analysis and inferential statistics, and standardized the features
- Utilized unsupervised learning algorithms such as KMeans for model fitting and clustering
- Did PCA to reduce the dimensionality of the features for data visualization, and evaluated the model using Silhouette score

Machine Learning for supervised and unsupervised related projects Jul 2017 to Sep 2017

- Applied different typed of supervised learning algorithms for different datasets.
- Applied the different types of clustering algorithms
- · Evaluated the performance of each clustering algorithms and selected the model with good score

Inferential Statistics based Analysis

Jul 2017 to Jul 2017

- Applied statistical analysis for three different dataset
- Developed hypothesis for each dataset and tested them

SQL Analytics: Investigating a Drop in User Engagement dashboards Jun 2017 to Jun 2017

- Set up different possible hypothesis for the problem
- Applied SQL analytics to test the hypothesis, and identified the possible problem

Analysis of copper concentration using reflectance band ratio & Oct 2010 to Dec decision tree 2010

- Cleaning the data and did exploratory data analysis using Excel Macros
- Utilized decision tree algorithm to identify the influential spectral reflectance bands using R
- · Did PCA to reduce the dimensional space and applied spectral band ratio of ASTER satellite of the area
- · Analyzed and correlated the results from decision tree and spectral band ratio, which were very good fit

SKILLS

PROGRAMMING AND SOFTWARE SKILLS:

python (including packages such as NumPy, scikit-learn and Pandas; ggplot,matplotlib, Bokeh), R, Machine Learning, MySQL, Java, Visual Basic, BI visualization tools, Microsoft offices, ArcGIS, ERMapper, SES, Drillworks Predict